hey guys today I'll teach you how to
solve the 2x2 Rubik's Cube using a
beginner method so the first thing we'll
do is build an entire layer on any color
but I'm going to use white for this
tutorial and what I mean by a layer is
not only have this face salt and I'll be
white but also have these colors around
it line up so once your cube is
scrambled I'm just going to start with
white and I see white white white white
so there are four options of which one I
want to start with so I can just say I'm
going to start with this one it doesn't
matter which one you choose and then
just put it on the bottom like this so
that is going to be my first solved
piece so once you choose which one you
want to be solved look for white pieces
in the top layer so for example we have
this one over here so remember to keep
this on the bottom at all times this
white piece has green and red also on it
look at your original soft piece and we
have red and blue so the color they have
in common is red because of that I want
this piece to be next to the red here in
other words this piece is going to be
solved when it is over here so now what
I'm going to do is turn the top layer so
that it goes directly above the spot I
said it was going to go in to because
it's got red here and this red here so
it's going to go next to it here now to
move this one from the top into the
bottom make sure you're holding it in
your right hand like this not in your
left hand and then repeat this sequence
of moves make sure you get the sequence
of moves down because it's going to be
very important later on as well so hold
your left hand like this and hold your
right hand like this with your thumb on
the bottom then repeat after me turn the
right side up
push the top with your right hand turn
the right side down push this off with
your left hand so you're going to repeat
that until this corner is solved so do
we see white on the bottom here no we
don't so we're going to repeat
and this is white on the bottom but it's
not the piece we were looking for as you
can see that's not the red piece so
we're going to go again
and there it is now we have a soft piece
so what we can do is keep repeating this
so we look in the top layer for white
pieces we see white here and this has
orange and blue on it so look at what
we've already solved we have blue red
and green so the color they have in
common is blue
so that means this one must go next to
the blue piece over here
so we're going to move the top until
it's directly above that spot
hold it in the right hand and then
repeat those four moves until this one
is in here
so once
and nope the White's not on the bottom
yet twice three times four times five
times sometimes it takes up to five
times and then now it's in there and
just make sure the colors here match as
well and for example the last piece here
we find a white piece and a top layer
it's got orange and green so well
there's only one last spot for it so
we're just going to move it in here and
repeat the four moves until it's in
there
and there we go there's the first layer
one situation you can run into is your
first layer is not done but there's no
more white pieces in the top layer so in
that case it might just be in the bottom
layer and how to remove it into the top
layer so you can do what you normally do
is just put it on the right side like
this and repeat the four moves that
moves it up into the top layer without
breaking your progress and then once
it's in the top layer you can just put
it into the spot it should go into
normally so once you finish the first
layer and check that all the sides here
are the correct then we're going to move
on to the last layer so focus on any
particular bottom layer piece I'm going
to choose this one which has red and
green on it but it doesn't matter which
one you pick then try and solve the
corner that goes directly above it so
we're going to turn the top layer until
we see red and green and it's this one
this one has yellow red and green now
we're going to check every other piece
on the top and see if they're in the
correct spot and count how many we have
so here we have red blue and this one's
red blue so this one's correct blue
orange not blue orange so this one's
incorrect green orange not green orange
so this one's also incorrect so in this
case we happen to have two that are in
the right spot so your goal for this
step is to get all four in the correct
spot if they all were in the right spot
already then you're done this step but
if you cannot get all four in the
correct spot then you only want one in
the correct spot not two like I have
here so for example in this one I could
just do another turn instead and we find
that only this one is in the correct
spot and every other one is in the wrong
spot so this is good now sometimes you
won't be able to get all four and you
won't be able to get only one in that
case you'll just do what I'm about to
show from anywhere but if you only get
one in the correct spot then you want to
hold it on the front right like this
next what you do is this algorithm
that's quite easy to memorize because it
has a nice pattern to it so turn the top
with your right hand turn the right side
up now repeat this with your left hand
top with your left hand left side up now
the exact same thing but all downwards
this time so top of your right hand
right side down top with your left hand
left side down so once you've done this
this one should still be in the correct
spot but every other one should have
moved so check if they're in the right
spots and they're not so that means
we're just going to repeat it again
top of the right right side up top with
the left left side up and then all down
top of the right right side down top
with left left side down and now we
check them all again and they're all in
the correct spot so what we do is see
that okay all the top pieces have yellow
on them here which means yellow is what
goes on the top here so what we're going
to do is turn it upside down and hold
any unsolved piece here at the bottom
right and so we're going to repeat the
four moves that I showed in the
beginning until the yellow here faces
the bottom so I'm going to do it once
like this
twice
three times
four times
and there we go now once this one is
solved we're going to go on to the next
corner but instead of just rotating the
whole Cube to go to the next Corner this
will mess up your whole Cube so instead
we're just going to stay facing the same
side but then turn the bottom only to
grab the next Corner over
then we're going to repeat until this
corner is solved
there we go it's solved and then we move
on to the next one
and repeat
and there it is then that's the whole
thing lastly if you want to get faster
links are in the description for more
advanced methods thanks for watching and
I'll see you guys next time hey guys
this video will be example solves for
the 2x2 beginner method so I'm going to
start by looking for white pieces to
make the white layer and I can start
with any piece I want put that on the
bottom and then this is green and orange
so I'll look in the top layer for
another white piece and it's this one
this one's